Guide to the Katharine R. H. Lyman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Katharine R. H. Lyman papers
1932-1937
MS 1914
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.05
(4 boxes)
The papers comprise approximately one hundred letters between Katharine Lyman and her mother, photograph albums, scrapbooks of clippings, and two videotapes, all depicting the daily life of the Chinese, political and military events, and staff at Peking Union Medical College Hospital in the 1930s.
Lyman, Katharine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers are the gift of Peter Coxe, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Associated Materials
Two books were transferred to the East Asia Library, Yale University Library. One map was transferred to the Map Collection, Yale University Library. Additional information available in the repository.
Biographical / Historical
Katharine Russell Ham Lyman was born in Brookline, Massachusetts, on August 9, 1894. She graduated from Radcliffe College with an A.B. degree in 1918. She was employed as a hospital social worker, 1918 to 1926, in the Boston and Pittsburgh areas, as well as assistant director of social work at Strong Memorial Hospital, 1926 to 1931, during which time she met her future husband, Richard S. Lyman (1891-1959), a neuropsychiatrist from Johns Hopkins Hospital. After their wedding in Germany, she traveled with him to Peking, China, where he worked at the Peking Union Medical College Hospital as associate professor of neurology and psychiatry and she worked as volunteer supervisor in the social service department. The Lymans returned to the United Sates in 1937 after the Japanese capture of Peking, eventually to work at Duke University of Medicine, North Carolina, in their respective fields. In 1943, Katharine Lyman worked in Washington D. C. for the Office of Strategic Services preparing lectures on Eastern culture for paratroopers. Katharine Lyman died in West Orange, New Jersey, in January 1994.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise approximately one hundred letters between Katharine Lyman and her mother, photograph albums, scrapbooks of clippings, and two videotapes, depicting the daily life of the Chinese, political and military events, and staff at Peking Union Medical College Hospital in the 1930s.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945; Beijing (China); Lyman, Katharine; Lyman, Richard Sherman; Xie he yi yuan (Beijing, China)
- Biographical information, 1960-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence between Katharine Lyman and her mother
  Scope and Contents
  Describes Lyman's daily life and discusses the political and military situation in China.
  - 1932 August 26-1935 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - 1935 December 27-1937 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photograph albums
  - Trip to Jehol, 1937 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Japanese bus through Kupeikou to Jehol in Marichukuo, then boat down Luan River to Peking.
  - Angkor Wat, Bali, Cambodia, Japan, Java, Korea, Macassar, Siam, Suez Canal, and Sumatra as well as China, circa 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Scrapbooks
  - Scrapbook detailing background events leading to "kidnapping" of Chiang Kai-shek, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, 1933-1937 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- An Eight Month Experiment, circa 1937; videotape (VHS) (Box 3)
  The approximately 40 minute film consists of a sequence of scenes in a Peking psychiatric facility following a progression of treatment of some of Dr. Lyman's Chinese patients. It includes: 1933 Summer, Palace of Prince Na, Quarters, The Next Move, Delousing, A Further Extension Was Necessary, Three Months Pass - Snow, Teaching Clinics, Going Home, Dr. Fang Inspects, Men Private Patients, Women Private Patients, and Occupation.
  - Use copy, 1 (Box 3U)
- Scenes of daily life, primarily in China, circa 1937; videotape (VHS) (Box 4)
  The approximately 40 minute film includes: Lei Tai-Fu Arrives (assumed to be Dr. Lyman arriving home), Taking Down Ping, Central Park, Street Scenes, Street Kitchens, Miss China 1937, Chinese New Year, Ling Fu SSU, Peiping Union Medical College, Social Service Unit, Yenching University, Pilgrimage to Maio Feng Shrine, Street Parade, U.S. Troops Parading, Japanese Planes July 1937, Summer Palace, Pei Hai, National Library, Temple of Heaven, Funeral Procession, U.S. Marines, Belka (Mrs. Lyman's horse), Lei Hwang Teh (Mrs. Lyman's dog), and Ting Tsien (the woman who appears a few times is surely Mrs. Lyman).
  - Use copy, 1 (Box 4U)